Guide to the Max Lerner Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Additional Material, Accession 2005-M-032
  - Writings (Box 10)
    - Diaries (Box 10)
      - 1941 January-1945 December, 14 (Box 11)
      - 1946 May-1989 December, 14 (Box 12)
      - 1990 February-1991 February, undated, 6 (Box 13)
    - Books
      - America & Its Discontent [title uncertain], 1976-1986, undated; 10 (Box 14)
      - America Ascendant Dance [title uncertain], 1988-1991, undated; 12 (Box 15)
      - Eros in America, 1956-1981, undated (Box 15)
        - Drafts, 7 (Box 16)
        - Correspondence (Box 17)
        - Correspondence and drafts (Box 17)
        - Publishing plan (Box 17)
        - Research files, 7 (Box 17)
      - Europe [book on Europe, possible title: The Creative Continent], 1962-1966, undated (Box 18)
        - Agenda, outline & themes (Box 18)
        - Chapter I, 2 (Box 18)
        - Chapter II (Box 18)
        - Chapter III (Box 18)
        - Chapter VI (Box 18)
        - Chapter VII (Box 18)
        - Chapter VIII (Box 18)
        - Chapter X (Box 18)
        - Crucial outlines of book (Box 18)
        - General ideas, 2 (Box 18)
        - Paris notes (Box 18)
        - Research notes, 4 (Box 19)
        - Workbook (Box 19)
      - Memoir [autobiography], 1928-1992, undated (Box 19)
        - Drafts, 12 (Box 20)
        - Drafts, 5 (Box 21)
        - Correspondence, 10 (Box 21)
        - Research notes, 10 (Box 22)
      - Supreme Court [may be related to Nine Scorpions in a Bottle], 1961-1988, undated (Box 22)
        - Drafts, 7 (Box 23)
        - Research files, 2 (Box 23)
        - Research files, 10 (Box 24)
    - Screenplay [title: White Robe Black Robe], 1980, undated; 3 (Box 25)
    - Short writings (Box 25)
      - America Agonistes, Undated (Box 26)
      - Ardors and Tribulations of the Journey of Liberalism, 1989, undated (Box 26)
      - Assessment of Space Mss, 1985, undated (Box 26)
      - Book reviews, 1966-1989, undated; 3 (Box 26)
      - Bork's Progress, 1987-1988, undated (Box 26)
      - Divorce and Remarriage of Political Economy, Undated (Box 26)
      - Dream Sequence, 1968-1970, undated (Box 26)
      - Education, undated (Box 26)
      - Extremism, Undated (Box 26)
      - From Bork to Kennedy: the Confirmation Legacy, 1987, undated (Box 26)
      - Future, 1967 (Box 26)
      - Gandhi, 1983 (Box 26)
      - How to Face Human Extinction: A Response to Jonathan Schell, 1982, undated; 2 (Box 26)
      - Human Rights Symposium, 1981, undated (Box 26)
      - Is America a Dying Civilization?, 1973; 2 (Box 27)
      - Jefferson, Thomas [short writings about], Undated (Box 27)
      - A Judge Touched by Fire, Undated (Box 27)
      - Kissinger Enigma, [1976?] (Box 27)
      - Lerner on Law [compilation of Lerner writings on the law], 1987 (Box 28)
      - Letter from Yugoslavia, Undated (Box 29)
      - A Man Angry at Death, 1965, 1970, undated (Box 29)
      - Meta-Man: Redefining and Integrating the Human Experience, 1983-1984, undated; 2 (Box 29)
      - Myth America, 1987 (Box 29)
      - Notre Dame [lecture?], 1978-1983, undated (Box 30)
      - Reading-No Dying Art, 1978 (Box 30)
      - Some Questions that Don't Stay for an Answer, 1980-1983, undated (Box 30)
      - Surprising Presidency, 1985 (Box 30)
      - Ten Ways of Looking at a Civilization, Undated (Box 30)
      - Terrorism, 1983, undated (Box 30)
      - Third-Century America: an Overview, 1976 (Box 30)
      - TV-Third House, Fourth Branch, 1969-1970, undated (Box 30)
      - We Were All Reds in Those Days, 1930s-1982, undated (Box 30)
      - Miscellaneous, 1975, undated (Box 30)
    - Columns (Box 30)
      - 1970, 8 (Box 31)
      - 1972 (Box 31)
      - 1985 (Box 31)
      - 1987, 2 (Box 31)
      - 1988 (Box 31)
      - Miscellaneous, 1960-1984 (Box 31)
    - Lectures (Box 31)
      - Chautauqua [original audio cassettes], 1989 (Box 32–33)
      - Max Lerner and Hugh Hefner at ADL Reception [original audio cassette], 1980 (Box 34)
  - Teaching materials (Box 34)
    - Brandeis University [Politics 172a: Contemporary Europe], 1962-1969, undated; 9 (Box 35)
    - New School for Social Research, 1983-1990, undated; 2 (Box 35)
    - Notre Dame, 1983-1984, undated; 3 (Box 35)
    - United States International University [various courses], 1974-1990, undated; 6 (Box 36)
    - Unidentified (Box 36)
  - Personal (Box 36)
    - Articles about Lerner, 1957-1987, undated; 5 (Box 37)
    - Hefner, Hugh [transcription of conversation between H. M. H. and Max Lerner], 1978 (Box 37)
    - Hospitalization, 1981-1991, undated; 2 (Box 37)
    - Love musings, 1962-1978, undated (Box 37)
    - Photographs, Undated (Box 37)
    - Publicity [re: lectures], 1984-1985 (Box 37)
    - Ted and the Kennedy Legend [book reviews], 1980 (Box 37)
    - Who's Who in America [includes other directory materials], 1959-1991, undated (Box 37)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 37)
  - Research files and notes, 1950s-1990s, undated (Box 38–42)
- Additional Material, 1950-1998; Accession 2011-M-019
  The materials in this accession are arranged in the following sections: writings by Max Lerner, writings about Max Lerner, and writings by others. When possible the handwritten titles or notes on the original folders have been used. Researchers should be advised that some folders include not only the material under which subject heading they appear, but also clippings, notes, research materials, and correspondence. Materials relating to each of Lerner's unpublished books, and the posthumously published The Wounded Titans, have been placed together for ease of use.
  - Writings by Lerner
    - Articles
      - 1950-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
      - Brown, Jerry, notes and newsclippings, Circa 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - "Desire and Power in the White House", Circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Los Angeles Times Syndicate: "The World of Our Children" and "What Happened to the Revolution?", 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "A Wounded Civilization", 1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Book reviews, 1975-1991 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
      Includes reviews of books about John F. Kennedy.
    - Books
      - American historical documents anthology
        - Mind and Faith correspondence with Allan Ecker, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        - Soul of America
          - Documents list, Circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
          - Preface, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
          - Suggested/possible documents, foreward, Circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
          - Table of contents, correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        - W.W. Norton and Company, publishers
          - Draft of foreward, carbons, list of documents to be used, Circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
          - Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
          - Proposal, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Column anthologies
        - Column titles, listed chronologically, 1959, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
          Includes summaries for columns written from January to June 1959.
        - 1960s proposal, 1969-1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
          Proposed titles include Wheel of Fire, Stormy Present, and The Sixties: Dispatches From the Cultural Wars.
        - 1970s proposal, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)
          Proposed titles include The Stormy Present and Hot and Cool History: Perspectives from the 1970s.
      - Eros in America, correspondence and research material, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Memoir, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 23-25)
      - Wounded Titans, 1978-1995 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
    - Columns, 1959, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Foreword to Roy Hoopes' Ralph Ingersoll: A Biography, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Journal pages
      - 1988 January 3-March 6 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - 1988 July 23-November 26 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - 1990 November 5-December 10 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - For "heart" chapter, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Lectures and speeches
      - Inauguration as W. Harold and Martha Welch Professor of American Studies at the University of Notre Dame, September 17, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Notre Dame lectures, 1983 March-May (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - "The Structure of American Society," National War College, September 16, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Transcripts of speeches, 1950-1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Notebooks
      - "America Ascendant", 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - "Great Judges", 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Notes for columns, Circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - "Total Person" notes, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - "Illness" journal notes, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Notre Dame sexuality course, 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Change I, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Life-human behavior class notes, 1978-1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "A Possible Sequence", Circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      A listing of proposed and in-process books.
    - "The Shaping of American History", Circa 1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Historical chart, in about 125 dates, of important and symbolic events in American political, social, and cultural history.
    - Syllabi and class notes, 1952-1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Writing plans, 1975-1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Writings about Lerner
    - Articles, clippings, and reviews, 1958-1998 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Bain, George William, Liberal Teacher: The Writings of Max Lerner, 1925-1965, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Microfilm copy flow of dissertation for Ph.D. in Modern History, University of Minnesota, 1975.
  - Writings by others
    - Articles and newsclippings, 1957-1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - The New Republic, 1958 March 10 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Schmuhl, Robert, "American Crude", 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Souter, David Hackett, "Holmes' Legal Positivism and the Criticism From a Current Position of Natural Law", 1961 April 10 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Senior Honors Thesis, Department of Philosophy, Harvard University.
    - Toynbee, Arnold, "No, America is part of a wider, Atlantic, community", Circa 1957 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Commentary on America As a Civilization.